Guide to the Homewood-Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation Records, 1984-1988,2017 AIS.2014.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Homewood-Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation Records
1984-1988
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hawkins, Matthew
Birru, Mulugetta
Homewood-Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation
AIS.2014.04
2.13 Linear Feet (1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box)
The records of the Homewood-Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation (HBRDC), founded in 1982, contain correspondence, meeting minutes and supporting documents detailing the group's campaigns and advocacy activities. The collection also contains the group's monthly newspaper, The Homewood-Brushton Informer, which was active from 1984 to 1988. The focus of the HBRDC was on housing, business and urban redevelopment projects.
History
The Homewood-Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation (HBRDC), founded in 1983, was a community-based institution that worked to counteract increasing urban blight in the predominantly African-American Homewood-Brushton neighborhood of Pittsburgh. Funded primarily through the Pittsburgh Partnership, The HBRDC operated as part of a larger movement of Community Development Corporations (CDC) during the mid-1980s which targeted its efforts on housing and economic development and improvement projects in low-income urban neighborhoods.
The Homewood-Brushton Informer newspaper, first published in July 1984, served as HBRDC's vehicle for community outreach and information, reporting on news regarding housing, business and redevelopment projects in Homewood-Brushton as well as cultural happenings, city politics and commentary on broader national racial and political issues. The newspaper had a readership which grew from 3,000 people in 1984 to 39,000 people by 1987, making it one of Pittsburgh's most popular African-American news publications.
Led by Director Mulugetta Birru, a native Ethiopian, and Matthew Hawkins, a Homewood-Brushton resident who served as Associate Director of the HBRDC and Chief Editor of the newspaper from 1984-1988, the group also worked to provide social services to the community through job training workshops, establishment of a credit union, day-care programs, senior centers and minority youth employment drives. The group also engaged in efforts to improve the business profile of Homewood-Brushton by financing shopping centers, business "incubators" and retail franchises both owned and staffed by residents of the neighborhood.
Previous Citation
Homewood-Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation Records, 1984-1988, 2017, AIS.2014.04, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
The collection consists of materials documenting the activities of the Homewood-Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation which are organized by relevant correspondence, annual meeting minutes and supporting documents that are divided and labeled in folders reflecting the group's various campaigns and advocacy activities from 1984-1988, which focused on issues such as youth employment, business and residential district revitalization and senior housing. The collection contains the Homewood-Brushton Informer newspaper dating from July 1984 to March 1988. The records also contain a few photographs of the Homewood-Brushton neighborhood in the late 1980s along with several printed maps of the neighborhood and Pittsburgh's East End and a small amount of newspaper clippings covering the group's activities.
Arrangement
Records are arranged in two series:
Series I: General Files
Series II: The Homewood Brushton Informer Newspaper
Acquisition Information
Gift of C. Matthew Hawkins on October 31, 2014.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
African Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; City planning -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Community development -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Economic development -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Economic development projects -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Homewood (Pittsburgh, Pa.); African Americans -- Housing -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Urban renewal -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Associations; Ethnic groups; African Americans -- Employment -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Hawkins, Matthew; Birru, Mulugetta; Homewood-Brushton Informer; Homewood-Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation
- General Files, 1984-1988, 2017; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The General Files series consists of various office, administrative and project files of the organization.
  - 615 N. Lang Street Development Project, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Board Meetings, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Associate Director Job Description, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Business District Revitalization Program, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Community Development Consortium Report, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Community Reinvestment Act Meetings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Corporation Board Meeting Minutes, 1986-87 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Corporation By-Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Corporation History, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondences, 1987-88 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Development Potential for Homewood South Business District/EL Crow Study, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Effort to Prevent Demolition on Frankstown, Susquehanna and Bennett Streets, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Executive Director's Report, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Homestead Credit Union Project, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Homewood-Brushton Roundtable Project, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Homewood South Developer's Information Kit, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Housing Study of Homewood-Brushton, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Interview with Matthew Hawkins, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Low Cost Housing Strategy, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Market Study for Informer Newsletter, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minority and Women Business Enterprise Project, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Minority Youth Employment Task Force, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Mission Statement, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Neighborhood Maps, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - News Clips, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photos: Homewood-Brushton, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pittsburgh City Planning Commission Hearing Report, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Scope of Services Statement, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Senior Housing Project, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Sewing Co-Op, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - State of the Corporation Report, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Strategy for Community Economic Development, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "A Look Inside Homewood's Economic Development: 1950s-1990s," by C. Matthew Hawkins, no date (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "Corrective Capitalism: The Rise of America's Community Development Corporations, A Report to the Ford Foundation" Booklet, c. 1987 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Homewood Brushton Informer Newspaper, 1984-1988; II.
  The Homewood Brushton Informer Newspaper Series consists of issues of the official community oriented publication of the Homewood Brushton Revitalization and Development Corporation. While the collection is missing some issues, it consists of a very comprehensive run of the publication from its inception in 1984 through 1988.
  - Volume 1, Issue 1, July 1984 (Box 2, Item 1)
  - Volume 1, Issue 2, August 1984 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Volume 1, Issue 3, September 1984 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Volume 1, Issue 4, October 1984 (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Volume 1, Issue 5, November 1984 (Box 2, Item 5)
  - Volume 1, Issue 6, December 1984 (Box 2, Item 6)
  - Volume 2, Issue 1, January 1985 (Box 2, Item 7)
  - Volume 2, Issue 3, March 1985 (Box 2, Item 8)
  - Volume 2, Issue 4, April 1985 (Box 2, Item 9)
  - Volume 2, Issue 5, May 1985 (Box 2, Item 10)
  - Volume 2, Issue 6, June 1985 (Box 2, Item 11)
  - Volume 2, Issue 7, July 1985 (Box 2, Item 12)
  - Volume 2, Issue 9, September 1985 (Box 2, Item 13)
  - Volume 2, Issue 10, October 1985 (Box 2, Item 14)
  - Volume 2, Issue 11, November 1985 (Box 2, Item 15)
  - Volume 2, Issue 12, December 1985 (Box 2, Item 16)
  - Volume 3, Issue 1, January 1986 (Box 2, Item 17)
  - Volume 3, Issue 2, February 1986 (Box 2, Item 18)
  - Volume 3, Issue 3, March 1986 (Box 2, Item 19)
  - Volume 3, Issue 4, April 1986 (Box 2, Item 20)
  - Volume 3, Issue 5, May 1986 (Box 2, Item 21)
  - Volume 3, Issue 6, June 1986 (Box 2, Item 22)
  - Volume 3, Issue 7, July 1986 (Box 2, Item 23)
  - Volume 3, Issue 8, August 1986 (Box 2, Item 24)
  - Volume 3, Issue 9, September 1986 (Box 2, Item 25)
  - Volume 3, Issue 10, October 1986 (Box 2, Item 26)
  - Volume 3, Issue 11, November 1986 (Box 2, Item 27)
  - Volume 3, Issue 12, December 1986 (Box 2, Item 28)
  - Volume 4, Issue 1, January 1987 (Box 2, Item 29)
  - Volume 4, Issue 2, February 1987 (Box 2, Item 30)
  - Volume 4, Issue 3, March 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 5, May 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 6, June 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 7, July 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 8, August 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 9, September 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 15, November 8-14, 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 16, November 15-21, 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 17, November 22-28, 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 19, December 6-12, 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 22, December 20-26, 1987
  - Volume 4, Issue 23, December 27-January 2 1988